Now we had a look at compression and headers, now logging is also something that matters. For that
I'll quit my server and I'll install a new package with npm install --save and that is called
morgan and that is a package that makes logging request data
really simple.
Now after adding it, I can, whoops, restart with npm run start dev, my nodemon server and now to use
morgan, I'll import it here in the app.js file, I'll require morgan like this and now we can use it as
a middleware,
also before we handle all the requests, so also maybe up here, we app use morgan and we execute this
as a function and pass the information on how to log this into this function.
Now you find more in the official docs, that simply defines which data is being logged and how it's formatted,
I'll go with combined
and now if I save that and I reload this page here, you'll find some logging data here in the console.
You see detailed logging information about the incoming request that we had a get request, which browser
I used which operating system and so on.
Now obviously we typically don't want to see that in the console when we deploy our application
instead some files would be nice and to log that to files, we just have to add something here,
we can create a new constant, the access log stream, use the node file system which is a core module which
we have to import by requiring
fs here
and now with that, we can create a write stream with create write stream
and this allows us to then define a path best with path join, seen from our current folder on to let's
say access.log so that we will write the logs into this file.
We will add a configuration here where I set flags to a which means append,
so new data will be appended to that file and not overwrite the existing file but add it at the end of
the file so that we don't just have one log statement in the file but we continuously add them to the
file
and now this write stream can be used by morgan and we simply pass that stream to morgan in a second
argument. Here we can set a stream value in that object and we set that, whoops, not here but in the morgan
function here,
so here we set the stream and we set that to our access log stream here.
And now this file stream will be used by morgan to log our requests and therefore now if I reload
this page,
we don't have the log here but we have this new access log file and in here, we see that log data and
that is of course how we would want to log that
but also as mentioned on the slide, often logging is done by our hosting providers
so then this might not matter for you. If you want or have to do it manually though, this is a nice package
where you can of course configure more as you can see in their official docs which allows you to log
your request data to files
so that you always know what's going on on your server.